Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert Du Motier, Marquis de Lafayette, Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert Du Motier, Marquis de Lafayette, Papers 1776-1934
MSS83543
Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert Du Motier, marquis de, 1757-1834
300 items
2 containers plus 3 oversize
1.4 linear feet
1 microfilm reel
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Soldier and statesman. Correspondence, legal documents, clippings, broadsides, orderly book, photographs, and other papers relating chiefly to Lafayette's military service in Canada and Virginia, his tour of the United States from 1824 to 1825, his land in Florida, and his views of such topics as the slave trade and the French government, including also material pertaining to the centennial observance of his death and Lafayette's genealogy.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Clarkson, Thomas, 1760-1846--Correspondence.; Custis, George Washington Parke, 1781-1857--Correspondence.; Gist, Mordecai, 1743-1792--Correspondence.; Graham, George, 1770-1830--Correspondence.; Greene, Catharine Littlefield--Correspondence.; Holmes, Abiel, 1763-1837--Correspondence.; King, Charles, 1789-1867--Correspondence.; Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert Du Motier, marquis de, 1757-1834.; Laurens, Henry, 1724-1792--Correspondence.; Vaudoyer, Antoine, 1756-1846--Correspondence.; Willett, Marinus, 1740-1830--Correspondence.; Woodford, William, 1734-1780--Correspondence.
Subjects
Real property--Florida.; Slave trade.
Places
Canada--History--1775-1783.; France--Politics and government.; United States--Description and travel.; United States--History--Revolution, 1775-1783--Campaigns.; Virginia--History--Revolution, 1775-1783.
Occupations
Soldiers.; Statesmen.
Provenance
Papers of Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert Du Motier, Marquis de Lafayette, soldier and statesman, were acquired by the Library through gift and purchase from 1907 to 1956.
Related Material
A related collection in the Manuscript Division is the Marquis de Lafayette Papers, 1757-1990 in Chateau La Grange, available only on microfilm.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert Du Motier, Marquis de Lafayette, are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Microfilm
A microfilm edition of part of these papers is available on one reel. Consult reference staff in the Manuscript Division concerning availability for purchase or interlibrary loan. To promote preservation of the originals, researchers are required to consult the microfilm edition as available.
Scope and Content Note
Papers related to Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert Du Motier, Marquis de Lafayette (1757-1834) span the years 1776 to 1934 and include correspondence, legal documents, clippings, broadsides, an orderly book, photographs, and other papers.
The collection includes material concerning Lafayette's military service in Virginia and Canada, his tour of the United States in 1824-1825, his land in Florida, and his views on such topics as the slave trade and the French government. Also included is material relating to the centennial observance of his death and Lafayette's genealogy.
Correspondents include Thomas Clarkson, George Washington Parke Custis, Mordecai Gist, George Graham, Catherine Littlefield Greene, Abiel Holmes, Charles King, Henry Laurens, Antoine Vaudoyer, Marinus Willett, and William Woodford.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged by type of material.
Container List
Selected correspondence available on microfilm. Shelf no. 4390
- Correspondence (Box 1)
  - Originals, 1778-1834, undated (Box 1)
  - Reproductions (Box 1)
    - Facsimiles of letters from Jules Cloquet to Isaiah Townsend relating to Lafayette, 24 Aug.-7 Nov. 1834 (Box 1)
    - Photocopies, 1777-1834, undated, (2 folders) (Box 1)
    - Typescripts (Box 1)
      - Letter from M. Narbonne to Lafayette, 8 Feb. 1792, with enclosure and explanatory note by William C. Lawton, Apr. 1923 (Box 1)
      - Letters from Lafayette to Antoine Laurent Thomas Vaudoyer, Noailles Lafayette, and Hubert Robert, 1800-1815 (Box 1)
- Miscellany (Box 2)
  - Agreement by Lafayette to serve in the Continental Army, 7 Dec. 1776 (facsimile) (Box 2)
  - Briscoe, Ruth L., "The Influence of the General Lafayette Memorial Flag," paper read before the thirteenth annual meeting and state conference of the Maryland Society, Daughters of the American Revolution, 14 Mar. 1918 (Box 2)
  - Card admitting Miss Rutherford to a ball in honor of Lafayette, Orange Spring, 19 Oct. 1824 (facsimile) (Box 2)
  - Clippings relating to the Lafayette statue, Place du Carrousel, Paris, France, 1889-1900, undated (Box 2)
  - Clippings about the Lafayette statue at Metz, France, 1907-1908, undated (Box 2)
  - Genealogy of Lafayette, presented in, 1907 See Oversize (Box 2)
  - Harmon, Artemas, "General Lafayette's Visit in 1824," 29 May 1934 (photocopy) (Box 2)
  - Invitation to a ball in honor of Lafayette, Nashville, Tenn., 7 Apr. 1825 (Box 2)
  - Lafayette's address to the U.S. House of Representatives, 10 Dec. 1824 (photocopy) (Box 2)
  - Lafayette's oath of loyalty to support the cause of the United States, 9 June 1778 (Box 2)
  - Lafayette's power of attorney conferred on George Graham, 2 Sept. 1825 (Box 2)
  - Lafayette's power of attorney conferred on James Madison, 9 Oct. 1804 (photocopy) (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous photocopies, 1785-1789, undated (Box 2)
  - One hundredth anniversary of the death of Lafayette, messages, addresses, and program, 20 May 1934 (Box 2)
  - "Order of Exercises," including odes to Lafayette, 6 Sept. 1934 (Box 2)
  - Order to obtain bills of exchange on France to repay Baltimore, Md., merchants for sums advanced to Lafayette, May 1781 (Box 2)
  - Orderly book kept by members of the staff of Generals Lafayette, Poor, and Hand, 9 Aug.-16 Sept. 1780 (Box 2)
    - Original (Box 2)
    - Photocopy (Box 2)
  - Photographs of Chateau Lafayette, undated See Oversize (Box 2)
  - Picture badge of Lafayette, undated (Box 2)
  - Trip aboard La Victoire, 1777 (photocopies) (Box 2)
  - United States warrant drawn in favor of Lafayette for his services during the Revolutionary War, 1825 (photocopies) (Box 2)
- Oversize (Box OV 1)
  - Miscellany (Box OV 1)
    - Genealogy of Lafayette, presented in, 1907 (Container 2) (Box OV 1)
      - Manuscripts (Box OV 1)
      - Portraits (Box OV 2)
    - Photographs of Chateau Lafayette, undated (Container 2) (Box OV 3)